<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Windows on Living Systems_</title>
    <link>https://livesys.se/tags/windows/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Windows on Living Systems_</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Nov 2018 16:36:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://livesys.se/tags/windows/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Setting up a reasonable and light-weight Linux-like (non-WSL) terminal environment on Windows</title>
      <link>https://livesys.se/posts/linux-like-non-wsl-terminal-env-on-windows/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Nov 2018 16:36:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://livesys.se/posts/linux-like-non-wsl-terminal-env-on-windows/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was looking for was a no-fuss, lightweight, robust and as simple as&#xA;possible solution to running my normal Bash-based workflow inside the&#xA;main Windows filesystem, interacting with the Windows world. Turns out&#xA;there are some solutions. Read on for more info on that.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;windows-subsystem-for-linux-too-heavy&#34;&gt;Windows Subsystem for Linux too heavy&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;First, I must mention the impressive work by Microsoft on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/wsl/about&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Windows&#xA;Subsystem for Linux (aka.&#xA;WSL)&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;, which more or&#xA;less lets you run an almost full-blown distribution of popular Linux&#xA;distros like Ubuntu and Fedora. WSL is awesome, but also kind of heavy,&#xA;easily taking something closer to an hour to install. It also has some&#xA;odd behaviours like opening files in Windows from WSL will give you&#xA;troubles with line endings (as you might know Windows uses &lt;code&gt;\r\n&lt;/code&gt; for&#xA;line endings while Linux uses just &lt;code&gt;\n&lt;/code&gt;). Finally, the default bash&#xA;terminal for WSL did not even have zoomable text. All in all, this made&#xA;it clear that this is not the light-weight simple solution I was looking&#xA;for. WSL is awesome, but too heavy that I will be comfortable to quickly&#xA;install it on any Windows machine I need to spend time working on.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
